Okay, in this video we are going to
discuss closing procurement, right,
closing out the contract with the vendor.
Now, close procurement, closing out your
procurement, can occur in one of two ways.
First, by completion of the contract.
The vendor has performed the work,
so now we can go into closing.
Now we can close out the contract,
completion of the contract.
That's the best way to close out a
procurement.
But there's another way as well.
early termination of the contract.
So you've got completion of the contract
and early termination of the contract.
So let's talk about the completion of the
contract first.
Then we'll talk about early termination on
the next slide.
So completion of the contract,
right?
The seller has performed the work,
right, to our adequate standard,
to our satisfaction.
And now we can pay them and close out the
contract.
And that's what completion is.
The seller's work has been complete.
been successfully delivered to the
customer.
A lot of times, just a written notice has
been given from the buyer or written notes
from the buyer have been given to the
seller.
The state work has been done.
We've accepted the product and now the
contract is closed.
And of course, with a completion of the
contract comes the final payment.
Until the final payment is made,
then the project is still open.
The project is not closed until you have
the final payment.
So again, as a very simple example, you're
doing some work in your house, right?
You've hired some vendors to perform some
work in your house.
Well, you're satisfied
the work with the work or,
you know, they've done
the work, you pay them.
Now the contract is done.
So that's one way of closing out the
procurement completion of the contract.
The other way then is by early termination
of the contract, early termination.
And the three types of early termination
or cancellation.
You have a cancellation
for convenience, cancellation
for cause, cancellation
by mutual agreement.
So let's talk about each of these.
Cance for convenience.
Now, cancellation for convenience is a
right only for the buyer.
Only the buyer has this right.
And that is basically stating
that the buyer can cancel
the contract early due to
various business reasons.
Right.
And these business reasons have to be
negotiated.
and written in the contract.
So it's a very simple example.
Let's say, halfway
through the project, senior
management decides to cancel the project.
And you have hired a whole bunch of
vendors to work on this project.
And now the project is canceled.
We got all these vendors.
What are we going to do with them now?
So what we would have done, right?
What we should have done is we would have
negotiated a cancellation for convenience,
as we were negotiating
the contract, we'd negotiate
a cancellation of convenience
with these vendors.
That would have stated.
If this situation is to occur,
right, if situation was to occur where
senior management cancel the project,
then we will cancel the contract early.
We'll pay for all the work that you've
done up until that point, right?
And, you know, penalties and so and so
forth, right, we'll pay for all of that.
But the contract is now closed.
The contract will need to be cancelled.
And this is a right only for the buyer.
So it's a no harm, no foul type of
situation.
And obviously, you know,
since a seller is signing
the contract, the
seller has to agree to it.
Right.
So that is a cancellation for convenience,
right?
Only a right offer to the buyer.
Then you have something called a
cancellation for cause.
And a cancellation for cause is for both,
buyer and seller.
and it refers to a cardinal breach of the
contract.
A cardinal breach means a material breach.
So basically, one party defaults on the
contract.
So, the other party can take legal action.
That's what cancellation for cause is.
If either party defaults on the contract,
then the other party
can take legal action.
That's specifically known as a
cancellation for cause.
And then you have this one called a
cancellation by, mutual agreement,
right, and as the name suggests,
that should be self-explanatory.
If either party wants to cancel the
contract early, then as long as the other
party agrees by mutual consent,
then the contract can be closed early,
or it can be cancelled early.
And again, this is a
right for both buyer and
seller, so it's by mutual
consent of both parties.
All right, so these are the types of early
termination, cancellation for convenience,
cancellation for cause cancellation by
mutual agreement right and then the two
ways of closing a contract two ways of
closing a procurement is by one of the
previous slide completion of
the contract and on this slide
cancellation or early
termination of the contract okay